So now we're going to bring this all together
and we're going to build a simple programmable,
flexible, programmable central processor building
it all with gates. Okay, it's not going to be very
sophisticated, but it's going to be a programmable
processor. So let's go back to the beginning of my
Python class and look at this picture again
where we have a central processing unit that
has registers and arithmetic logic units and it
processes instructions and in the main memory
we have the code and data. And so when we write
a program we kind of are putting ourselves into
that main memory. The central processor asks what
next and that says give me the next instruction
and those that next instruction is a series
of binary numbers zeros and ones coming out
of the memory of the computer. Then it decodes
that instruction and it says what am I going
to do? Maybe load some load a value from memory
store a value from memory perform a calculation
inside the central processing unit. And then when
that's done, the central processing unit says,
"Give me the next instruction." And then the main
memory gives the next instruction. And since this
is a oversimplified generic computer, suitable
for a very beginning Python programming class,
but let's use a little more advanced terminology
that you will eventually hear. So inside the CPU,
there's a thing called the arithmetic logic
unit. We call it the ALU. It's like the adder
code. We've already built a three-bit adder. That
would be in the arithmetic logic unit. When they
mean logic, they mean comparison, like if tests.
If tests are checked, like is x less than zero?
That's part of the logic part of the arithmetic
logic. Registers are temporary places to store
data in the CPU that does not require going
to and from memory all the time. We've already
built a register. We built a three-bit latch,
which I also told you was a threebit register.
And then what we have is programs and they come
from the memory. And so the the memory has a
series of program instructions. The CPU has what's
called a program counter, and it retrieves the
next instruction, decides what kind of instruction
it is, and then sends signals to the registers
and the ALU, whether it's loading data or storing
data or making computations. Coming up very soon,
we're going to actually design a simple CPU that
has machine language. It's going to be a complete
architecture. It will have a machine language
and an assembly language completely defined and
we will write programs in this little machine
language. Now it's called the CDC 8512 because
when I was young and starting just starting out I
programmed on a computer called the control data
corporation CDC 6500 and back when the computer
museum in in Seattle was open they had a running
one of these things and I have a video which
I will share with you. Um, unfortunately, uh,
with the passing of Paul L and that that museum,
uh, closed, but that's that's unfortunate. So,
I've seen one running recently. I've got some
video and I will share that with you, but that's
that's not what we're doing right now. I'm just
telling you that what we're doing right now is a
step toward building a real live full function CPU
with machine language and data, etc. So, but now
we're going to build a really, really simple CPU.
It's going to have one register. It's a three-bit
latch. It's going to have two machine instructions
that we can inform the CPU what we want done. And
it has a clock that happens every second. So, it
runs one of two instructions every second. The
zero instruction, again, it's machine language,
clears the latch, and the one instruction tells
the latch to add one to itself. And like I said,
this is going to happen once per second and we
can submit a zero instruction or a one instruction
once per second. So we're going to have this built
and it's going to run on our emulator. This is the
CPU. The emulator has a clock. It has a three-bit
latch which is our register. Then it has an adder.
One of the operands to the adder is the output of
the latch. The other operand to the adder is a one
hard-coded one and then you take the output of the
adder. Now before we had run this straight into
the latch so that the it would just add one every
time. But now what we have is some decoding logic.
So if the instruction is zero, recall the latch
is supposed to be set to zero. If the instruction
is one, we're adding one to the latch every clock
pulse. And that clock is going up and down once
per second. The part that we've added here from
the previous example is this logic. When you look
at real CPUs, you're going to see that they have
a series of control logic. And what does the
control logic do? It reads the next instruction
from memory and it does what's called decoding it.
And then it distributes signals to give orders to
the rest of it. And so in this case what's going
to happen is this andgate is going to block the
output because we just put ands. We are running
the the one two and four column of the sum through
the ANDgate and then we're hard- coding zero the
instruction zero to the other inputs of the three
and gates. And so the output of those AND gates if
the instruction is zero is zero no matter what the
other inputs are from the adder. Okay. So we'll
start this with instruction zero. So every time
the clock goes, the inputs to the latch are all
zeros because the instruction input is a zero
and zero and anything is a zero. So clock tick
tick tick. Every time this clock is ticking, that
latch is resetting, meaning copying zero from its
inputs. So the adder is like happily adding one
to the zero but that's it because the adder inputs
are being blocked from coming back into the latch
by the endgates. So you see when the instruction
is zero the endgates function as a block in effect
turning off the data going into the the latch. Now
we're going to switch the instruction to one and
we wait one clock pulse. So then what happens is
the one instruction going to the three and gates
is no longer blocking data. So whatever the
outputs are coming from the adder are passing
right through the okay in this particular case the
adder has a four that is presenting a four at the
input. Four's column is a one and the two's column
is a zero and the ones column is a zero. While
the clock is low, that four is at the input to the
register/latch. And then when the clock goes high,
then we'll copy the four into the latch. In the
beginning, you start with the instruction zero,
the latch is zero, the adder is one, but
the zero instruction is blocking data to
go back into the latch. It's blocked because
it's a zero instruction. On the other hand,
if there is a one instruction, then this functions
like a counter. That means every second it goes up
by one. So when the clock is high, it copies
the input. Then the clock goes low. Then the
the latch value goes to output the adder adds
one. Then when the as long as the instruction
stays one and the clock goes high, the output of
the adder is once again copied into the latch. So
it's a very simple two instruction computer. We
simply touch the instruction. We program this by
touching the instruction value switch and setting
it to zero or one. So this is a two instruction
computer. What's missing? Well, really it's
really hard to build a CPU where you can reach
in and touch a button and have the instruction be
the button that you touched. The clock rate is,
you know, megahertz, not one hertz. and so you
can't send the instruction. So really what you
want is a flexible way to store and retrieve
instructions so that the instructions can be
presented to the CPU fast enough to keep up with
the clock rate. So we really want a flexible long
sequence of many instructions executed one after
another which we would call software or a program.
So up next, we're going to think about how
we might store sequences of instruction in
the memory and then retrieve those instructions
from the memory and then execute them in the CPU.
Wait just a second. There were
a lot of switches on the front
of a Colossus's computer in a
video from an earlier lecture.
Yes, the earliest computers did have
switches on the front to control program
behavior. These switches often controlled
conditional variables, so program behavior
could be changed while flipping a switch
while the program was running. Actually,
those switches were more like the variables
that could be changed on the front panel.